Welcome
back.
We've been dealing mostly with UML class
and object diagrams in the last few videos.
You can see now
here on the slide,
in the title at least, that
we're talking about an activity diagram.
That's a different
kind of UML diagram.
And that's even though we haven't actually gotten to
the part of the lecture where we're going to be
dealing with
UML activity diagrams.
We are actually in
the Petri net part.
So why does
this diagram appear here?
First, simply as an
example of a UML
diagram that is
about dynamic modeling.
Here it is about modeling a
process, how a house should be built.
Details are not
so important now, because
we will look at this example in more
detail in the lecture in a few weeks.
What this is about right
now is that these UML
activity diagrams can be simplified
to be represented by Petri nets.
Petri nets are a simpler mechanism
that goes towards UML activity diagrams.
The current lecture material for the next two
or three weeks will be these Petri nets.
You can use
them (just like activity
diagrams) when you
need to model processes.
That is, processes that
consist of individual steps.
The main point
is to specify
or formulate and summarize conditions
under which certain single steps
are executable or in which
order they have to happen.
At first glance, this may look
a bit like a flat state diagram.
So like what we have
dealt with in the Wolf-Goat-Kohlkopf problem,
for example, or
in the corresponding exercise.
But if we look closely, we see
that there are not just nodes and connections
here, in the simple way that
there were in flat state diagrams.
There are extra elements
here, also highlighted graphically.
So this kind of
node or this apparent distribution
node where the
flow branches out.
Then you have
to talk about
what that should mean (as semantics)
of these two places in the diagram.
We'll do
that, of course.
But for now, it may suffice
to observe that, by design, there
is obviously more going on here
than in a very simple graph.
This is also a kind of graph, but not
the simple kind of graph where we only have,
as in a flat
state diagram, nodes and transitions.
We'll look at that
in more detail later.
But in the coming weeks, we'll look
at a simplified version, in a sense, of
activity diagrams like
this, via Petri nets.
And later, the relationship
to the UML world.
So what
are Petri nets?
Petri nets will
look like this.
It's a little bit
different, maybe simpler, because
there are fewer different graphical
elements than in the slide before.
We're going to have essentially these
two types of nodes in a graph.
These round places are
called places, or places actually.
And there can
be markers (tokens) in there.
These will be movable little markers (tokens) afterwards
that can be moved through the Petri net.
And these boxes, these are another
kind of nodes in the graph.
They are
called transitions.
And they essentially play the role
that the individual actions play here.
So those are used
to model dynamic actions.
While these places and the markers (tokens)
on them will rather stand for resources
that are used or
needed for these actions.
Petri nets are clearly
a means for dynamic modeling.
As opposed to class and object
diagrams, which are made for static modeling.
This is also
stated here again.
So emphasis is
on modeling dynamic behavior.
Petri nets are
a fairly old approach.
They go back to work done a
long time ago by a Mr. Petri,
hence
"Petri nets".
Unlike many
other model mechanisms
that we cover in the
lecture, they have very formal semantics.
So they are
really precisely mathematically defined.
And also the questions
about Petri nets can all
be defined mathematically, and we
can also give proofs of them.
We won't do that here, but in the
lecture you should get to know a very
formal mechanism in addition
to the more intuitive
and semi-formal modeling
methods of UML.
This is also a motivation
why Petri nets are part of
this course, and no
small part at that.
You probably won't be familiar
with Petri nets from school,
but possibly from the pre-course in
computer science, if you took that.
And some of you,
maybe not the Komedia
students, but the computer science
and ISE students, may encounter Petri
nets again
in other courses.
That could be in courses
on operating systems, real-time systems,
or at the latest in the master's when
you hear Distributed Systems or courses with Ms. König.
We start
with an introduction.
Now in this video still rather informally,
to give you simply again more motivation.
On another example, which I will discuss
in more detail at this point already as
the house building example
that we just saw.
And then this week and next week it
will be about the formal basics, and the representation,
and the expression of the dynamics,
and the concept of reachability graphs.
Then that's sort of the semantics
of Petri nets unfolded, capturing all
the flows of
a Petri net.
But that's probably going to
be on our minds next week.
I had
already mentioned:
Petri nets are a formalism
of dynamic modeling, for certain situations.
So whenever it is
somehow about representing transitions.
I mentioned actions earlier, or single
steps in a run of a system.
And often, at least
in the background, maybe even
in the foreground, is
the handling of resources.
We have a system where
certain steps are allowed to
run, but only
under certain conditions.
So in the house construction example,
there was the position of a
plan that was created, that is dealt
with, that perhaps has to be checked.
And there it may
be that certain steps in
this process are only possible
if such a plan exists.
Or in another
system, those resources
might actually
be material resources.
Like in the snack vending machine example
that I briefly talked about last week.
There, that could just be
the snacks and the chip packs
or cookie packs that were available,
or the money from the vending machine.
Those would all be things
where you're talking about resources.
And those can be
captured well in Petri nets.
And easier than, say, in
a very simple graph where you
have to represent
all the states.
In the snack machine example
last week, I talked about how
there would be almost 4000 states if
you wanted to capture all possible constellations
of the machine through
a flat state diagram.
This will be realized differently
and more simply in Petri nets.
On the one hand, this allows
us to model something like capacities well.
For example, that the
snack machine has a
certain maximum capacity
for its respective resources.
On the other hand,
the spatial distribution of resources.
So if we
somehow imagine systems
where it matters where
certain resources are stored, and
concepts like concurrency and
parallelism play a role.
I'll talk about that briefly on
a slide in a moment as well.
And whenever
we have resources
that are perhaps used by
different consumers, there can be conflicts.
And that's also going to be a
central concept in the analysis of Petri nets:
When or if there are conflicts between
different actions in the Petri net, for example.
And what is also
peculiar to Petri nets:
That they have a
fairly intuitive graphical representation.
One defines Petri
nets mathematically, but
they also allow for a graphical representation,
which is what we will largely work with.
However,
not exclusively:
We will also
definitely build the
bridge to the
mathematical, set-theoretic representation.
As far as practice is concerned, I
have already mentioned some areas of application.
At least mentioned where you
might encounter this in your studies.
For example, in distributed systems,
in the modeling of distributed
systems, or in the
analysis of distributed systems.
And I already mentioned that in
the UML language family, which is widely
used in software engineering, Petri
nets as such do not exist
(directly in the representation as
found here and also in books).
But the activity
diagrams present in UML
are slight variations, and other
representations ultimately, of Petri nets.
We will also want
to build this bridge later.
Now I had just
mentioned concurrency and parallelism here.
I would like to clarify
these terms on the next slide.
What
is parallelism?
This is the
everyday term for parallelism.
So things take place
in parallel, that is, simultaneously.
From everyday life, there is
the phenomenon in many places.
And of course also in computer science,
for example, there are many situations of parallelism.
So maybe if you have a game
graphics card, you might have thought about
how many parallel operations it
can perform before you bought it.
There is talk that in order
to render many polygons at the same
time, this graphics card should have many
efficient processing cores that should work in parallel.
Parallelism plays
a role here.
For example, when it comes to computer
efficiency, parallelism is a typical measure these days.
What
is concurrency?
It sounds
something like that.
Something is running
side by side.
That also
sounds like parallelism.
Yet, there is
an extra term here.
Concurrency is basically more the
mathematical requirement for things to
happen in parallel or
to be processed in parallel.
So we'll talk about
concurrency of individual actions
in a
Petri net.
And what will
be meant by that
is that they can/may be executed in
parallel, but they don't have to be.
That is, if there is no causal dependency
between them (for example, they also do not
interfere with each other, for example
because they want to access the same
resources in a conflicting way),
then these actions will be concurrent.
There will be a formal
definition of what that means.
And thus concurrency is
the more general term.
Because only when actions are concurrent, so
to speak, no problems would arise from
their parallel execution, then we
can actually implement them in parallel.
Formally, we will
deal with concurrency.
But the motivation for that will
be that we want to capture
situations where parallel
execution would be possible.
And of course there are lots
of examples where that becomes relevant.
I had just mentioned these computations
in a graphics card, for example.
But also
any other application
on a computer
will often have concurrency.
For example a GUI
and calculations in a spreadsheet:
Even while calculations are taking place
(perhaps a process is running that performs
the calculations in the spreadsheet), we still
want to be able to operate the GUI.
And not be slowed down somehow, and
not be able to operate the program.
This is then possible because
the GUI operations and the
graphical application operations are
concurrent with the calculations.
Because they don't
access the same resources.
And how that is then implemented
exactly, whether or not two different
computer cores actually perform these two
actions, is not so relevant for that.
That's an
implementation detail.
What's important is establishing
the concurrency of these
two processes,
computing and rendering.
And of course you
can find many other examples,
even in the
everyday world, of concurrency.
So any
banking system:
If you go into a branch of
a bank and operate a statement printer, and
a family member of yours is
at the same time perhaps making
transfers at another terminal, then
somehow the system should be realized
in such a way that
these actions can be implemented concurrently.
So that the bank has
control over the fact that incorrect
states are not created in the system
by the execution of these two actions.
For example, there is resource access to
the money or to the account balances,
and then, please, that should
run correctly in each case.
And there could be a modeling
with Petri nets in the background.
Probably in the concrete case it
will be a more complicated modeling tool
than just Petri nets,
which is in the background.
But the questions can be
asked already for Petri nets.
This is
quite abstract.
I had already promised that we would
also look at a simple but concrete
example already
in this video.
This is an example that
you may well have encountered before.
This is a typical
also playful computer science problem:
The so-called
Dining Philosophers.
This exists
in various forms.
I'm actually looking at the simplest
version here, with only three philosophers.
It is also possible
to formulate with more
philosophers, and also with
other arrangements of these philosophers.
In our simple case,
we have three philosophers
sitting around a round table
who obviously want to dine.
These are the dining philosophers, that is,
they are hungry and would like to eat.
There is also
no shortage of food.
So there is actually a plate
of food in front of everyone.
But there is a scarcity
of tools to eat this food.
Because the three philosophers
together have only three forks.
We imagine these three
philosophers P1, P2, P3.
They sit around the table, and there are
the Forks, the forks, and also three in number.
And they lie
exactly between the philosophers.
So far
so good.
The problem is that
when the philosophers are
hungry and want to eat,
they need two forks each.
So even though they have food in
front of them, they can't do anything
with it unless they have two
forks (one in each of their hands).
You
see:
Now obviously the three philosophers
can't eat at the same time.
Then you would need at least
six forks, but there are only three.
The question
is, of course:
How do
they agree?
Or, can
What happens when
one philosopher gets hungry?
Well, then that philosopher has
to pick up the two forks.
And the philosophers do this
according to a very strict scheme.
They may have committed themselves beforehand
and are inflexible in their actions.
In any case, they always have
to behave in the same way.
Namely, a philosopher always
needs both forks for
eating, and takes
the right fork first.
So P2 would take F1
first, then the corresponding left fork.
Then P2 would eat and put
both forks back at the same time.
Now one can already ask
certain questions at this simple system.
So, can several philosophers
eat in parallel here?
Is parallelism
possible here?
One can already think about that
on the basis of the forks and
philosophers that it
will not work.
Because already if two philosophers wanted to
eat, they would need four forks together.
There are only three forks,
so parallelism is not given.
Is there perhaps something finer
at least between individual action concurrency?
So maybe reaching for the forks
is at least independent of eating?
This can be investigated when we
have described the system more precisely,
when we have made
these verbal rules more firm.
We will
do that later.
We will represent this system as a
Petri net and then answer such questions formally.
What we can
already consider informally here
is that there can be
problems here in any case.
That maybe the
philosophers are actually
starving because they can't
get to the food.
For example, because of their stubbornness to
always reach for the right fork first and
then, independently,
the left fork.
Thus, in an unfavorable
case, it could happen
that, for example, P2 reaches for F1,
and before P2 can reach for F2, P3
reaches for F2 (because P3 has also become
hungry and also reaches for his right fork first).
If then the unfavorable case occurs that P1
also becomes hungry and reaches for F3, then each
of the philosophers would have a
right fork in his hand, and
none of the philosophers would have
a left fork in his hand.
So no one would
be able to eat.
But unfortunately, this would
not cause any of the
philosophers to put their
right fork back either.
Because their stubborn behavior,
as described above, is:
Grab right fork, then grab
left fork, eat, put it back.
So here, in the
worst case, if all three
philosophers grabbed the right fork,
the system would be "in deadlock".
That's what we'll
call it later.
So ultimately the philosophers have
to starve because together they have
maneuvered themselves into a situation
where no progress is possible.
That too, this kind of
deadlocking, we'll be able to
grasp formally in general terms for Petri
nets and then apply to cases like this.
So questions that arise
here for the example, but
just also for general
Petri nets, are things like:
Can the modeled system
continuously make further progress?
Is it the case that at any point
in time a further step is still possible?
This would not be
the case in this example.
Because in the case, where all three
philosophers have the right fork in each case,
but can neither reach for the left
one, nor eat, the system would be dead.
In fact, dead in the sense that
the philosophers will eventually starve to death.
Then we, or the philosophers themselves, would
have maneuvered the system into a dead end.
One wants to
avoid that in practice.
So one wants to be able to capture
that, when a system has this property or not.
Does every single modeled action get
the chance to actually be executed?
So if we have the system like on the
previous slide, is it even the case that every
meal action could be
executed at some point?
So even with good will,
is it at all possible that
every philosopher could get
a turn with food once?
Only once or even repeated
as many times as desired?
So, unless the philosophers are
somehow clumsy, would it be possible
for each of them to be allowed
to eat over and over again as well?
That's a question of
fairness in a sense, too.
For example, that two of the
philosophers can't starve the third philosopher.
You have to ask yourself whether the system
is fair in this or a similar sense.
These are properties that do not
only apply to this one system.
So fairness is also a question
that one can grasp in general,
and then ask for different
Petri nets and different systems.
Here I related it to
the philosophers in each case.
Are there dependencies
between the actions?
In that
case, sure.
We
know:
A philosopher can only eat when he
or she has the forks in hand.
So the fork-grasping is somehow
a causal condition for eating here.
That's obvious
in the example.
In other modeled systems, it
can be more interesting to figure
out what causal
dependencies exist between actions.
Because those may
not be immediately obvious,
and have to be inferred from
the behavior of the system first.
Actions can be conditional, but
actions can also contradict each other.
So they can
be mutually exclusive.
That an action
can never be executed
if another action would
also be possible, for example.
Are there restrictions
on resource consumption?
In the example just now, there would
be no obvious resource except for the
food, except for the forks, if
you also model them as a resource.
In the snack vending machine example mentioned earlier,
one might also ask whether there are inherent
constraints on the presence and
consumption of resources in the system.
So, for example, is the system designed in such
a way that it is never possible (not only
for external reasons, but for reasons of the system itself)
to have more than ten coins in the cash register?
What is written below does not
occur in this example, but will be
of interest to us
in the further course.
Namely that a Petri net
described also finitely can correspond
to an
infinitely unfolded system.
So it is possible to have Petri nets
which are finite (i.e. fit completely on a
slide, like the example just now),
but whose flat state diagram, in the
sense of the Wolf-Ziege-Kohlkopf graph,
for example, would be infinite.
And infinite things are
always hard to deal with,
but some of these analyses for Petri
nets are feasible (for the Petri net) even
if the corresponding flat
state diagram were infinite.
Then we derive a great advantage
from working with Petri nets instead
of naively just forming flat
state diagrams all the time.
We will encounter this when we
go deeper into the individual analyses.
We will not deal with
all of them formally here,
but at least the first, the second,
and to some extent the last two.
Practical applications then exist in many
areas of computer science or other fields.
There is the notion
of business process modeling.
There Petri nets or
related modeling mechanisms are applied.
Modeling of web services,
description of graphical user interfaces,
process modeling for operating systems
(where concurrency plays an important role).
In engineering applications
and many other
areas Petri nets or
similar mechanisms are applicable.
We will repeatedly pick up individual
simplified examples that may fall into
these domains, even
in the exercise mode.
We will not schedule an in-depth look at
exactly one of these domains in the lecture.
These are simply
a few keywords in
which domains Petri nets
or related mechanisms (such as
also the activity graphs)
can be found in practice.
We will of course look
at a few simple examples.